DevExpress CodeRush and Refactor=Pluralsight;Note=Erxin

# outline
- download address
http://visualstudiogallery.msdn.microsoft.com/1c5390ef-48a5-487c-9332-29b98efecc22
http://visualstudiogallery.msdn.microsoft.com/f9cda5d8-10af-4cc6-9d17-207222a3fd13
- coderush and refactor features
- tools that helps you get started
- basic configuration
- DXCore is the common basis, VS extensibility
	+ free download from devExpress
	+ enable developers to extend VS
- refactor, base on dxcore, pro is the full version
- coderush has all the other fetures
- coderush and refactor based on dxcore
- tools for extension
	+ guid panel
	+ code rush tool window
	+ tool bar, dxcore visualize.
- set up the parameters
	+ editor|code style 
	+ IDE|user info
	+ IDE|short cut could change the default short cut
	+ editor|selections|smart tags category

# understand existing code
- navigation features
	+ markers, dropping and collecting markers, automatic dropped
		* use alt + home combination to add marker
		* click escape key to return the marker position
		* the coderush will add temp marker
	+ bookmark
		* ctrl + alt+ number to add
		* alt + number to return
		+ ctrl + arrow to switch between the bookmarks
	+ tabbing between reference, shift tab
		* high light a identifier and hit tab or shift tab to jump between these identifer position
	+ camel case navigation
	alt + arrow keys to jump throw identifier names in identifiers
	alt + shift + arrow to select a word in camel case
	+ click identifier
		* ctrl + left mouse to click the identifer
		* press ctrl and hover the identifer will popup a window to display the defination of the identifier
	+ open file tool window and quick navigation
	the window will trace all the opened files currently in VS
	ctrl + f, quick switch files in the VS
	+ quick navigation
	ctrl + shift + q, will find the identifier by specify types
- visualization features
	+ flow visualization, display a icon after the line break the code flow
	+ there is a icon at each method
	+ the number in front of method could be changed to complex evalue, line number and so on
	+ the region has a special display range between the codes
	+ color have a real color line below the specify color, the color could be changed by click the color line
	+ the doc common is display block
- refactor tool window
	+ display the identifier or class reference detail in the current project
	+ there is a preview window
- running unite test
	+ have a tool bar of unite test runner
	+ add several icons into the unit test, and support many kinds of unit test framework
- configure features

# changing code
- member move, use the icon move the member function to region
- selection clipboard
	+ ctrl + c
	+ ctrl + b
	+ ctrl + w, ctrl + shift + w, to select range of code
- inteligent paste
- selection embedding
- changing visibility
- code provider, use the context menu
	+ change implet convert to explicit
	+ change for loop orientation
	+ move code to new file
- template
	+ open the tool window codeRush, it's a tool window to help understand the product

# code rush and refactor
- dxcore plug-in project
- plug-ins, tool-window
- system plug-ins
- load models for the plug-in
	+ start up
	+ idle
	+ demand
- extend one or more plug-in enable standard mechanisms
xxxProvider and xxxExtension components
- react to core events
- implement actions to be triggered
- use utility components for standard behavior
- the plug-in project is base on component
	+ drag the dxcore component from the toolbar to the component designer
	+ such as add string provider or action
	+ set the name and the direct event handler
	+ the project could run in debug model and this will open another VS to debug the code and host the new created plug-in
	+ configure the plug-in in the devexpress option page
	+ trigger the configure command to test the plugin
- option page












	
	