Hands-on windows phone 7 development=Yacine; Note = Erxin

# Intro, Agenda
- mvvm overview
- wp7 considerations
- sample app requirements
- application structure
- build the viewmodels
- build views
- navigations, phone relative
- commanding

# mvvm light framework, mvvm for windows phone 7
- model, the data for the application
	+ EF, entity framwork entities
	+ POCOs, class
	+ service types
- views UI components
	+ phoneApplicationFrame
	+ phoneApplicationPages
	+ controls
	+ code-behind
- viewModel
	+ bindable properties
	+ buisiness logic
- window phone 7 constraints
	+ wp7 navigation system, the start button and back button
	+ phone application lifecycle
		* maintaining app state
	+ data access and storage
		* occasionally connected situations
		* data and application lifecycle
- Implementation optons
    + list vew
    + details view
    + list viewModel contains details viewModel
    + mode object reference by the viewModel
    
    + Parent ViewModel and not child viewModel and parent view and detail view bind to the same viewModel
    
    + PRISM framework is used to separate cross boundary references
- the sample application
	+ express parcels company in the NYC area
        * drivers pickup and deliver parcels
        * drivers equipped with windows phones
	+ company uses in-house app to 
        * take phone reservations
        * track job status and throughput
        * manage invoicing etc
	+ drivers use app to manage jobs
        * view and available jobs
        * pick and update jobs
        * view and update parcels
    + Features
    each job can handle one or more parcels
        * a job can have more than one delivery address
        * driver updates each parcel status individually
    each driver is permanently assigned to a device
    driver can
        * view filtered lists of available jobs
        * assign a job to him/herself
        * update job status and pickup time
        * update parcel size class, delivery time and remarks
        * join a delivery receipt image to parcel
- Application Structure
    + add models, views, viewModel folder
    + add all data relative structure into Model, implement INotifyPropertyChanged interface for the one which need to be updated
    collection properties is ObservableCollection<Type>
        * Models
        Job, Parcel, Customer
        * ViewModels
        JobDetailsViewModel, JobListViewModel, ParcelViewModel
        * Views
        JobDetailsView, JobDetailsView, JobListView, ParcelListView, ParcelView
    + split the view logic at the viewModel also implment the INotifyPropertyChange interface
    + Custom the main startup page by the change, remove the mainPage
    change the ProjectName|Properties|WMAppMainifest.xml  change the <DefaultTask Name="_default" NavigationPage="CustomViewName.xaml"/> 
    change the main page to JobListView
- ViewModel Class
    + JobListViewModel, use code snippets to short the raise property changed method
    
    always avoid to directly access the model property instead of use other relative view model and make it to detail view model property and bind the property of this view model to help access the model property, example
    public ObservableCollection<ParcelViewModel> Parcels
    {
        get {
            return Job.Parcels.Select(p=> new ParcelViewModel{Parcel = p}).ToObservableCollection<ParcelViewModel>();
        }
    }
    
    + Add a helper class to add IEnumerable to help convert collection into ObservableCollection
    
    public staic ObservableCollection<T> ToObservableCollection<T>(this IEnumerable<T> list)
    {
        var col = new ObservableCollection<T>();
        foreach(var item in list)
            col.Add(item);
        return col;
    }
    
    public static void AddToObservableCollection(this IEnumerable<T> list, ObservableCollection<T> col)
    {
        foreach(var item in list)
            col.Add(item);
    }
- The main view  
    + use the App.xaml to add global properties, reference the App instance by App keyword
- View hierarchy
    + the ignore binding source expression will default to binding to the current data context {Binding}
    + binding the font and fontfamily to resources
    + binding the data template into 
    + add the resources to the App.xaml resource to make the resource could be access globally
- Navigation Topics
    + The phone's navigation model
    PhoneApplicatioFrame & PhoneApplicationPage enable easily switch are support by the NavigationService work with the phone's back button
    + Navigation history stack, NavigationService
    + Don't add custom back button which interfere with the default back button
    + Navigate() creates new page instance
    + Passing data around
        * using querystrings append to uri
        * use nested ViewMdels when use nested viewModels
        * global message bus, mvvmlight provide global message
    + example add PhoneApplicationPage.ApplicationBar control to help navigation
    change the added image property's build action to content
    
    to control the binding update time manually by set updateSourceTrigger=Explicit
    {Binding Parcel.SizeClass, Mode=TwoWay, UpdateSourceTrigger=Explicit}
    Then this will disable the autoupdate binding
    This feature is used to let the user manually cancel or save inputs
- Commanding ICommand, behaviors, MVVM Light
    + Zero code-behind approach for the view
        * View should not contain app logic
        * logic belong to view mode
    + UI logic should add into the View
    + An alternative approach:commanding & behaviors
        * Tie UI events to viewmodel logic
        * command capability is built-in silverlight 4 and not in WP7
        * MVVMLight for WP7, in lightweight manner
    + example, add reference MVVMLight dll, add command logic in view model
    ICommandObj = new RelayCommand(CommandCallback);
    
    + add reference to MVVMLight to xaml namespace MvvmLightCommand
    cmd:ButtonbaseExtensions.Command="{Binding ICommadObj}"
    
    + we could switch the datacontext for any UI element to make the UI switch between different datacontext, such as a button
    <Button DataContext="{Binding ElementName=this, Path=DataContext}"/>
    
    + the converter is set with static resource
- Takeaways
    + MVVM promotes SOC
    + Implementation should be phone-specific
    + Nested View Models is a simple option
    + Phone's model rules navigation
        
        
        
        
        
        