Numpy and scipy, neural network; notes = Erxin

:Numpy introduction 
>multidimensional array object for fast operations on arrays, including mathematical, logical, shape manipulation, sorting, selecting, I/O, discrete Fourier transforms, basic linear algebra, basic statistical operations, random simulation
>difference between standard python sequences
	- a fixed size at creation
	- in a arrary all required to be of the same data type, such as python sequences even nested numpy array
	- support advanced mathematical and fast than python build-in
	- more and more scientific and mathematical package use numpy arrays
>numpy array is vectorization and broadcasting
>numpy arrary object
	- ndarray.ndim, the number of axes
	- ndarray.shape, the dimensions of the array
	- ndarray.size, the total element number
	- ndarray.dtype, the element type of arrary, python-build-in or numpy.int16...
	- ndarray.itemsize, the size in bytes of each element
	- ndarray.data, contain th actual elements of array, normally use index to get element
	- ex.
	a = numpy.arange(15).reshape(row, col)
>create
	- by list and factory function
	numpy.array(enumerable_obj[, type])
	- The function zeros creates an array full of zeros, the function ones creates an array full of ones
	- arrange(start, end, step)
	- linespace(start, end, points_number)
>print arrary
	- ary.reshape
	- the large array will be only print the corners by default. to print all use the function set_printoptions(threshold='nan')
>operator
	- *, perform elementwise in numpy arrays
	- dot(), perform matrix product
	- += -=, modify an existing array
	- array object support normal mathmatic functions, the operation could be apply to one axies
	ary_obj.function(axis)
	- ..., represent as many columns as needed
>universal functions
all, alltrue, any, apply along axis, argmax, argmin, argsort, average, bincount, ceil, clip, conj, conjugate, corrcoef, cov, cross, cumprod, cumsum, diff, dot, floor, inner, inv, lexsort, max, maximum, mean, median, min, minimum, nonzero, outer, prod, re, round, sometrue, sort, std, sum, trace, transpose, var, vdot, vectorize, where
>indexing, slicing, iterating
	- support python type slicing
	- support slice each axis by list argument
	- iterater over multiple array object will iter by the first axis(row)
	- iterater each element over multiple array, use flat function
	- hsplit(a,3)   # Split a into 3
	- vsplit
	- use take method to slice the matrix
	array.take(indexes, axis)
>reshape the array
	- a.ravel() # flatten the array
	- a.shape = (6, 2), a.transpose()
	- reshape function returns its argument with a modified shape, whereas the resize method modifies the array itself
	- change the dimensions of an array, you can omit one of the sizes which will then be deduced 
>stacking together with different arrays
	- vstack
	- column_stack stacks 1d array columns into 2d, equivalent to vstack only for 1d
	- hstack
	- row_stack
	- r_[] and c_[] are useful for creating arrays by stacking numbers along one axis, default behavior like vstack and hstack, allow for an optional argument giving the number of the axis along which to concatenate
>copy and views
	- Simple assignments make no copy of array objects
	- The view method creates a new array object that looks at the same data. 
	- Slicing an array returns a view of it
	- The copy method makes a complete copy of the array and its data. 
>function and method overview	
Array Creation
    arange, array, copy, empty, empty_like, eye, fromfile, fromfunction, identity, linspace, logspace, mgrid, ogrid, ones, ones_like, r , zeros, zeros_like 
Conversions
    astype, atleast 1d, atleast 2d, atleast 3d, mat 
Manipulations
    array split, column stack, concatenate, diagonal, dsplit, dstack, hsplit, hstack, item, newaxis, ravel, repeat, reshape, resize, squeeze, swapaxes, take, transpose, vsplit, vstack 
Questions
    all, any, nonzero, where 
Ordering
    argmax, argmin, argsort, max, min, ptp, searchsorted, sort 
Operations
    choose, compress, cumprod, cumsum, inner, fill, imag, prod, put, putmask, real, sum 
Basic Statistics
    cov, mean, std, var 
Basic Linear Algebra
    cross, dot, outer, svd, vdot
>broadcasting rule, universal functions to deal in a meaningful way with inputs that do not have exactly the same shape. 
	- input arrays do not have the same number of dimensions, a "1" will be repeatedly prepended to the shapes of the smaller arrays
	- arrays with a size of 1 along a particular dimension act as if they had the size of the array with the largest shape along that dimension
>indexing and index tricks
	indexed by arrays of integers and arrays of booleans
	watch out if you want to use Python's += construct, as it may not do what you expect
>The ix_() function used to combine different vectors so as to obtain the result for each n-uplet.
	- inv, eye, dot, trace, solve
>matrix class, turn array object to matrix
	- matObj.T, transport matrix
	- matObj.I, inverse matrix
>comparing matrices and 2d arrays
Use of a single colon for the 2D array produces a 1-dimensional array, while for a matrix it produces a 2-dimensional matrix
>Histograms, apply to an array returns a pair of vectors, 
	
:scipy
>SciPy is a collection of mathematical algorithms and convenience functions built on the Numpy
>assume the main package import as:
import numpy as np
import scipy as sp
import matplotlib as mpl
import matplotlib.pyplot as plt
>subpackage description
cluster, 	    Clustering algorithms
constants, 	    Physical and mathematical constants
fftpack, 	    Fast Fourier Transform routines
integrate, 	    Integration and ordinary differential equation solvers
interpolate, 	Interpolation and smoothing splines
io, 	        Input and Output
linalg, 	    Linear algebra
ndimage, 	    N-dimensional image processing
odr, 	        Orthogonal distance regression
optimize, 	    Optimization and root-finding routines
signal, 	    Signal processing
sparse, 	    Sparse matrices and associated routines
spatial, 	    Spatial data structures and algorithms
special, 	    Special functions
stats, 	        Statistical distributions and functions
weave, 	        C/C++ integration
>help system, document, sp.info
sp.info(function_name/module)
>quickly construct array
sp.mgrid , sp.ogrid , sp.r_ , and sp.c_ for quickly constructing arrays.
r_, stand for row concatenation 
c_, column concatenation
>Polynomials, there are two ways to deal with 1-d 
	- poly1d, it is support deriv method poly1d_obj.deriv()
>vectorizing function, use vectorize to convert an ordinary function into vectorized-function
>useful functions
    - select(condition_list, chocie_list, default=0), is a vectorized form of the multiple if-statement
>common functions, place in scipy_base
factorial and comb functions, rand and randn, disp (similar to print), and who (returns a list of defined variables), derivative, central_diff_weights
>scipy special functions(scipy.special)	
    - airy, elliptic, bessel, gamma, beta, hypergeometric, parabolic cylinder, mathieu, spheroidal wave, struve, and kelvin
    - get help, help(special)
    - bessel function of real order(jn, jn_zeros)
>integration, scipy.integrate
    - get help, help(integrate)
    - quad          -- General purpose integration.
    - dblquad       -- General purpose double integration.
    - tplquad       -- General purpose triple integration.
    - fixed_quad    -- Integrate func(x) using Gaussian quadrature of order n.
    - quadrature    -- Integrate with given tolerance using Gaussian quadrature.
    - romberg       -- Integrate func using Romberg integration.
    - odeint        -- General integration of ordinary differential equations.
    - ode           -- Integrate ODE using VODE and ZVODE routines.
    - Gaussian quadrature, integrate.gauss_quadtol
        * fixed_quad 
        * quadrature 
        * special.orthogonal
    - integrating using samples, trapz , simps, and romb
    trapz, The trapezoidal rule approximates the function as a straight line between adjacent points
    simps, Simpson’s rule approximates the function between three adjacent points as a parabola
    romb, requires the number of sample points available is 2^k + 1 and k is integer
    - ordinary different equations, odeint
    special.airy, gives a means to check the integrator
>optimization package provides several commonly used optimization algorithms
    Unconstrained and constrained minimization of multivariate scalar functions (minimize) using a variety of algorithms (e.g. BFGS, Nelder-Mead simplex, Newton Conjugate Gradient, COBYLA or SLSQP)
        * minimize function provides a common interface to unconstrained and constrained minimization algorithms
        Broyden-Fletcher-Goldfarb-Shanno algorithm(BFGS)
        Newton-Conjugate-Gradient algorithm
        Constrained minimization of multivariate scalar functions
    Global (brute-force) optimization routines (e.g., anneal)
    Least-squares minimization (leastsq) and curve fitting (curve_fit) algorithms
        * Least-square fitting
    Scalar univariate functions minimizers (minimize_scalar) and root finders (newton)
    Multivariate equation system solvers (root) using a variety of algorithms (e.g. hybrid Powell, Levenberg-Marquardt or large-scale methods such as Newton-Krylov).
>interpolation, (scipy.interpolate)
    1-D interpolation (interp1d)
    Multivariate data interpolation (griddata)
    Spline interpolation
        Spline interpolation in 1-d: Procedural (interpolate.splXXX)
        Spline interpolation in 1-d: Object-oriented (UnivariateSpline)
        Two-dimensional spline representation: Procedural (bisplrep)
        Two-dimensional spline representation: Object-oriented (BivariateSpline)
    Using radial basis functions for smoothing/interpolation
        1-d Example
        2-d Example
>Fourier Transforms (scipy.fftpack)
discrete Fourier transform (DFT), fft, ifft, rfft, irfft
called the Fast Fourier Transform (FFT), fft in more than one dimension
>signal processing, scipy.signal
A B-spline is an approximation of a continuous function over a finite- domain in terms of B-spline coefficients and knot points
filter, signal.correlate,  signal.convolve
difference filter, signal.lfilter
>Linear Algebra (scipy.linalg)
    - scipy is use ATLAS LAPACK and BLAS libraries
    - The matrix class is initialized with the SciPy command mat which is also define in numpy(mat)
    - Solving linear system, using the scipy command linalg.solve
    - Finding Determinant, linalg.det
    - Computing norms, linalg.norm
    Solving linear least-squares problems and pseudo-inverses, linalg.lstsq will solve the linear least squares problem, linalg.pinv or linalg.pinv2 (uses a different method based on singular value decomposition)
    - Generalized inverse, linalg.pinv or linalg.pinv2
    - Decompositions
        * Eigenvalues and eigenvectors
        * Singular value decomposition
        linalg.svd will return U, V
        LU decomposition, linalg.lu
        * Cholesky decomposition, linalg.cho_factor 
        * QR decomposition, linalg.qr
        * Schur decomposition
        The command linalg.schur finds the Schur decomposition while the command linalg.rsf2csf
    - Exponential and logarithm functions
    inalg.expm, inalg.expm2, linalg.logm
    - Trigonometric functions
    linalg.sinm, linalg.cosm, and linalg.tanm respectively
    - Hyperbolic trigonometric functions
    linalg.sinhm, linalg.coshm , and linalg.tanhm
    - Arbitrary function
    Finally, any arbitrary function that takes one complex number and returns a complex number can be called as a matrix function using the command linalg.funm.
    - Special metrix
    block diagonal, 	scipy.linalg.block_diag 	Create a block diagonal matrix from the provided arrays.
    circulant, 	scipy.linalg.circulant 	Construct a circulant matrix.
    companion, 	scipy.linalg.companion 	Create a companion matrix.
    Hadamard, 	scipy.linalg.hadamard 	Construct a Hadamard matrix.
    Hankel, 	scipy.linalg.hankel 	Construct a Hankel matrix.
    Hilbert, 	scipy.linalg.hilbert 	Construct a Hilbert matrix.
    Inverse Hilbert, 	scipy.linalg.invhilbert 	Construct the inverse of a Hilbert matrix.
    Leslie, 	scipy.linalg.leslie 	Create a Leslie matrix.
    Pascal, 	scipy.linalg.pascal 	Create a Pascal matrix.
    Toeplitz, 	scipy.linalg.toeplitz 	Construct a Toeplitz matrix.
    Van der Monde, 	numpy.vander 	Generate a Van der Monde matrix
>Sparse Eigenvalue Problems with ARPACK

:neurolab library
>core 
Define Core Classes
class neurolab.core.Layer(ci, cn, co, property)
    Abstract Neural Layer class
    Parameters :	
    ci: int
        Number of inputs
    cn: int
        Number of neurons
    co: int
        Number of outputs
    property: dict
        propety: array shape example: {‘w: (10, 1), ‘b’: 10}
        
    init()
        Init Layer random values
        
    step(inp)
        Layer simulation step

class neurolab.core.Net(inp_minmax, co, layers, connect, trainf, errorf)
    Neural Network class
    Parameters :	
    inp_minmax: minmax: list ci x 2
        Range of input value
    co: int
        Number of output
    layers: list of Layer
        Network layers
    connect: list of list
        Connection scheme of layers*
    trainf: callable
        Train function
    errorf: callable
        Error function with derivative

    Connect format:	
    Example 1: for two-layers feed forwad network
        >>> connect = [[-1], # - layer 0 reseives the input network signal;
        ...            [0],  # - layer 1 reseives the output signal
        ...                  # from the layer 0;
        ...            [1]]  # - the network exit reseives the output
        ...                  # signal from the layer 1.
    Example 2: for two-layers Elman network with derivatives:

        >>> connect = [[-1, 0], # - layer 0 reseives the input network
        ...                     # signal and output signal from layer 0;
        ...            [0],     # - layer 1 reseives the output
        ...                     # signal from the layer 0;
        ...            [1]]     # - the network exit reseives the output
        ...                     # signals from the layer 1.

    copy()
        Copy network

    init()
        Iinitialization layers

    reset()
        Clear of deley

    save(fname)
        Save network on file
        Parameters :	fname: file name

    sim(input)
        Simulate a neural network
        Parameters :	
        input: array like
            array input vectors
        Returns :	
        outputs: array like
            array output vectors

    step(inp)
        Simulated step
        Parameters :	
        inp: array like
            Input vector
        Returns :	
        out: array
            Output vector
            
    train(*args, **kwargs)
        Train network see net.trainf.__doc__

class neurolab.core.Train(epochf, epochs)
    Base train abstract class
    error(net, input, target, output=None)
        Only for train with teacher

class neurolab.core.Trainer(Train, epochs=500, goal=0.01, show=100, **kwargs)
    Control of network training

    
    
    
    
    
    
    






	
	
	