电子商务专业教学中的问题及改善建议
Summary:There are two reasons of why E-commercial can't fully fit for the sociaty needs. First, the footing of high school is unclearly. Second, there is a practice gap between teaching and real world.
Keywords: E-commercial, teaching programme, practice

E-commerce is a new branch of science in recent years. It is rapid development, improve the growth of the emerging discipline. With the rapid development of e-commerce, the demand for talent in the field of community is more and more. The major colleges and universities have followed this trend and set up the E-commerce Business Program. However, the new professional, does not fundamentally fit for the social needs and reduce the pressure of the student employment. There are two reasons of why E-commercial can't fully fit for the sociaty needs. First, the footing of high school is unclearly. Second, there is a practice gap between teaching and real world.

First, the footing of the e-commerce professional.
E-commerce is a very general manner words. Many famous experts and scholars give its wide variety of different definitions, over the years. United Nations Economic Cooperation and Development (OECD), e-commerce is defined as occurring on an open network that contains business, commercial transactions between businesses and consumers. The U.S. government is defined as the business activities conducted through the Internet, including advertising, transactions, payments, services, activities. HP  define it as a way to be completed by means of electronic business and trade activities. Ultimately, the connotation of e-commerce is nothing more than a fusion of electronic and information technology and business. Therefore, the majority of college in the development of e-commerce teaching programs, add IT professional courses and marketing professional courses togther. Students' knowledge is indeed very wide, however, the accuracy, flexibility and integration of knowledge is obviously inadequate. After all, electronic information technology and marketing was originally two completely unrelated professional. The enterprise prefer to recruitment specialized electronics and information technology professionals and marketing professionals than the e-commerce graduate. So the significance of opening e-commerce professional is small.

In the 17 years since the development of electronic commerce, in terms of social recognition and economic value creation,it brings the decisive influence to the world.  From 1995 to 2010 , more than 125.0 billion dollars in venture capital investment to the network enterprise , and the only global online shopping in the online retail transaction size had reached 572.5 billion yuan. More enterprises in the world gradually moved into e-commerce market, the use of e-commerce to obtain greater profits. One of the most obvious yield advantage is to increase efficiency and reduce costs. E-commerce development in China for 15 years, is constantly creating new business opportunities. As of December 2010 ,  only create direct jobs of  Taobao reached 1.823 million , driven logistics, payment, marketing and other indirect jobs in the industry chain has reached over 500 million. More and more businesses and individuals understand the e-commerce, like e-commerce and start to benefit from e-commerce. Faced with such a large, better employment prospects, we must reflect on our graduates in the end can embark on what kind of jobs, and qualified for what needs?

This is the standpoint of electronic commerce professional college. The establishment of e-commerce professional should be to serve the society and open up market opportunities for foothold , to strengthen the cultivation of students' professional skills and ability. In the new market environment, Many of the employing unit needs are different from before, enterprises pay more attention to the type of professional talent that they desperately need. For example, many SMEs just want to walk the road of electronic commerce, but then e-commerce total lack of understanding, they can take advantage of e-commerce to increase revenue,but do not know how to start; those who are already successful practice of e-commerce road even need more staffs to solve the various problems in the process of e-commerce run. For different needs, we can also subdivide the professional students into three directions and types: skills-based,service-oriented and pioneering.

1.Skilled
E-commerce development in the field of space on the market, there are a lot of vacancies Facing these need be filled areas , need for more professionals to provide technical support and help. For example: Asia's largest retail shopping district - Taobao. Over the years, it has introduced a variety of strategies, including both for all of the electronic commerce participants provide marketing promotion, pay, logistics and technical support of basic services, and including "big clean out treasure" plan and "big logistics" plan, and so on. Taobao has become Asia's largest network of retail and business district, but the goal is dedicated to creating the world's preferred network of retail and business district. To increase the dependence of the online shopping population, and to carry out the buy mode, the online shopping population sustained attention Taobao, Taobao through a combination of the communities, rivers and lakes, gangs, and other personalized features. Taobao Mall integrate thousands of brands, manufacturers, and at the same time to carry out the C2C e-commerce mode, expand the B2C e-commerce model, to provide better services and protection for businesses and consumers. Provide 100% quality assurance of goods, seven days no reason to return after-sales service, and shopping points cash back and other services. Taobao the implementation of each action not only need to open up thinking, in fact, need the support of a variety of technical personnel. Therefore, for existing enterprises, technical personnel is particularly valuable.

2.Service
E-commerce can cut across traditional, established a substantial user-dependent and economic value, its pervasive service strategies are inseparable. Good service, both to ensure customer loyalty and increase word of mouth , to expand their markets, and stable income. However, the so-called service is very different from the traditional areas of service here, people are more stressed to meet the needs of people in the field of electronic commerce. This is actually very good  opportunity and challenge for our students. Service class talent is the key of e-commerce to seize the market context. Even the largest B2C e-commerce company in China - Jingdong online store will also be their brand by price first, service second shift as a "service first, price second. Jingdong Mall inception, adhering to the "people-oriented" service concept, the entire process for the user to provide humane "Family 360" full-service efforts to create a friendly, relaxed and enjoyable shopping environment for the user;It was originally management quality goods from the 3 C electronic products with field, and constantly enrich its product structure, so as to maximize the increasingly diverse shopping meet consumers' demand.

3.Pioneer
In fact, e-commerce itself can create opportunities, develop new markets, realize their business. Today, there are many new forms of e-commerce, such as mobile commerce, group purchase, expert online, etc., they penetration in every aspect of life, but has been not a particular style. Mobile e-commerce through mobile phones, PDAs, handheld computers and other handheld mobile terminals engaged in business activities. Group purchase is the group shopping, consumers together through the network, in order to obtain the optimal price of a way to shop.According to the principle of small profits, businesses can give less than the retail price buy discount and a separate purchase of a lack of quality service. Experts online through a unified platform provide consumers with high quality expert answer puzzled services online. Constantly innovate and develop a great change has been brought to the world, people's quality of life for all-round improvement, more and more emerging affairs are in order to better serve in daily life. School education must encourage the development of pioneering talent, and, as far as possible, to provide them with more support and help fully mobilize this type of talent to create a positive play to their strengths to create more new business opportunities and value, making increasing the quality of our lives.

Second, on the teaching and the actual derailment.
In addition to the various universities in e-commerce expertise foothold of teaching plans is not clear enough, the teachers engaged in e-commerce teaching and more computers, electronic information, economic, marketing, management, professional full-time teachers, and rarely have a dedicated e-commerce professional teachers teaching. Expertise among the teachers is not interoperable, they only introduce just pure knowledge within their respective professional to the e-commerce professional students, of students of e-commerce professional are not a single professional students  , carried out a large number of professional courses, the basis of professional teachers of various subjects taught in only on the surface knowledge of the course. This creates a problem, most e-commerce professional students feel that they learn a lot of courses, but not fine, it is difficult to be together, use in the electronic commerce in practice.

In this case, the teachers' level of business and teaching skills is particularly important.  The original subjects mechanically using apparently has been unable to meet the needs of society. Therefore, we need to make e-commerce professional teachers to accept and grasp more comprehensive domain expertise. Teachers to receive specific training to understand their professional skills in e-commerce in the end can play what role, and a good understanding of how the expertise to adapt to the real needs of e-commerce and other professional knowledge mastery. So as to drive the students to integrate theory with practice, more practice, more meaningful to the technical advantages of the original subjects fully used in the field of electronic commerce, culture really meet the needs of the community of professionals.

Such as knowledge of computer professionals, and more to provide technical support in e-commerce. In e-commerce, we need the support of the network environment, you need the support of the hardware environment, need the support of the software environment, need the support of the site components, more needs authentication, security, encryption and other support. Support precisely from the original computer professional. Computer professional teachers should focus on these aspects of e-commerce as a whole, with a focus to teaching to explain. Enable students to master in the field of electronic commerce, and focus to master the application of this knowledge and scope. Learn the used knowledge and skills, they will not feel these things has nothing to do with their own , and not know how to deal with.

In addition, examples of teaching in e-commerce teaching can not be ignored. As a new subject and emerging professional , theoretical knowledge on the books are not perfect, more accumulation of knowledge are often in practice. According to explore the actual case, pioneering the development of solutions can not only improve the students' enthusiasm for learning, but also better able to accumulate meaningful experience for teaching. These experiences often can become the cornerstone of the students into the community. Such as Alibaba's success stories, we can know the importance of courage and cover the face of e-commerce. Alibaba's 11 brands have developed, covering B2B (Alibaba) and B2C (Taobao Mall), C2C (Taobao) e-commerce model, covering the field of electronic payments (payment), the field of instant messaging (Ali Want), technical frontier (Ali) and other various fields. Be comprehensive coverage of the entire area of ​​electronic commerce within the group complement and support each other. Jack Ma, Alibaba Group Chairman of the Board of Directors proposed Alibaba's three ideals: to survive for 10 million businesses; create employment opportunities for over 100 million people around the world; online consumer platform for 1 billion people. The same time, we can also analyze the prospects for small and medium-sized traditional businesses, planning the introduction of e-commerce advantages, and its development of the introduction of e-commerce development strategy.

In summary, clear e-commerce professional foothold, training really adapt to the modern e-commerce businesses, technology-based, service-oriented and pioneering talent is one of the urgent problem of all colleges and universities to open e-commerce professional. Teaching and practice combine , theory guides practice, practice riches theory. Full professional knowledge mastery, not classroom teaching with the derailment. Producing graduates truly able to meet the needs of businesses and the community, explore new areas.






